Finding Aid for James W. Guthrie papers, 1845-1907
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James W. Guthrie papers 1845-1907
Guthrie, James W. (James Welch), 1827-1911.
0.4 linear feet
86648 Aa 2
Resident of Wooster, Ohio (later of Bedford, Iowa); 1862 graduate of the University of Michigan Department of Medicine and Surgery; surgeon in the 20th Ohio Volunteer Infantry during the Civil War. Civil War letters, diaries, newspapers, miscellanea and photographs; Civil War letters of his brother John Guthrie, also with the 20th Ohio Volunteer Infantry; and manuscript biography written by Helen Stephenson Guthrie.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Elizabeth Guthrie Foster (donor no. 6305 ) and came to the library in 1979.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
James Welch Guthrie graduated from the University of Michigan Department of Medicine and Surgery in 1862. He then enlisted as assistant surgeon with the 20th Ohio Volunteer Infantry. Following the war, he became a physician in Bedford, Iowa. He died September 27, 1911.
The collection consists of school records, and correspondence and other documents relating to his Civil War service and activities.
Subjects:
Bedford (Iowa); Iowa.; Ohio.; Physicians--Ohio.; United States. Army. Ohio Infantry Regiment, 20th (1861-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery. Class of 1862.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Medical care.; Wooster (Ohio)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Guthrie, James W. (James Welch), 1827-1911.; Medical aspects of war.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States. Army. Ohio Infantry Regiment, 20th (1861-1865)
Contributors:
Guthrie, Helen Stephenson.; Guthrie, John.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Personal and Civil War service
  - School records, undated, 1853-1854 and 1857 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated, 1845 and 1850-1859 (Box 1)
    - 1860-1862 (Box 1)
    - 1863-1869 (Box 1)
    - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
    - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
    - 1890-1909 (Box 1)
  - Civil War records, 1862-1865, including enlistment papers and special orders (Box 1)
  - Journal, undated, 1864 and 1875 (unbound) (Box 1)
  - Equipment requests and property indebtedness records, undated and 1862-1867 (Box 1)
  - Pension records, 1865-1907 (Box 1)
  - Battles fought by 20th Ohio Volunteer Infantry (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Newspapers, undated, 1863 and 1865 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of "Doctor Guthrie's War," undated (Box 1)
  - Notes, undated, by Helen Stephenson Guthrie on James Welch Guthrie (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1860 and 1864 (Box 1)
  - Photos of Guthrie and other soldiers, and photos of medical tools (Box 1)
  - Diplomas, 3 items
    (removed to library's diploma collection)